♪ ｢There was a famished crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢who somehow wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
♪ ｢if this beak was only longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢that feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢a crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
♪ ｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe. Formulate hypotheses. Experiment. Consider.
観察し 仮説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Learn the the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
We start with a ｢Thinking Observation｣.
まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
Today, observe this cup's shadow.
今日は このｺｯﾌﾟの 影 を観察する｡
If a finger's shadow nears the cup's shadow...
ｺｯﾌﾟの影に 指の影を近づけると…｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
The cup's shadow comes out and sticks to it.
ｺｯﾌﾟの影が くっついてきた｡
If we touch from above... →
上から 触 っても… →
the shadow stretches upwards.
伸びてくる｡
Let's try changing our hand's position,
手の位置を変えてみる｡
and put our hand on the other side of the cup.
ｺｯﾌﾟの向こう側に 手を持っていく｡
This time the finger's shadow lengthens.
今度は 指が伸びた｡
Even if we touch from above...
上から触っても…｡
the finger's shadow lengthens.
指の影が伸びる｡
Return our hand to its original position.
手の位置を元に 戻 す｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
As we'd expect, now the cup's shadow lengthens.
やはり ｺｯﾌﾟの影が伸びる｡
Even if we touch with a pencil... →
鉛筆 で触っても… →
it lengthens.
伸びる｡
Why should this be?
なぜなのか？
｢Thinking Observation｣.
｢考える観察｣｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Hello everyone.
皆 さん こんにちは｡
Today we present a problem using candles.
今日は ﾛｳｿｸを使った問題を 出します｡
If this candle →
このﾛｳｿｸに →
is lit...
火を付けて…｡
and we put this container over it...
このビンを かぶせると…｡
the flame
火は…｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
goes out.
消えてしまいます｡
Now, this is the problem.
では ここからが問題です｡
We put a different sized candle besides the first.. →
高さの 違 う２本のﾛｳｿｸを 並 べて →
and light them
火を付けます｡
then put the container over them. →
ここに このビンをかぶせると →
Which do you think will go out first?
一体 どちらが先に 消えるでしょうか？
Well, what will happen?
さてさて どうなるか？
Let's try it.
では やってみましょう｡
We'll show the answer at the end of the program. Everyone, please think about it.
答えは 番組の最後に発表します｡ 皆さん 考えておいて下さいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Observation, hypothesis, experiment and consideration.
観察 仮説 実験 そして 考察｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
And now, the answer. Everyone, did you think carefully?
では 先ほどの答えです｡ 皆さん ちゃんと考えましたか？
Okay then. Let's do it.
では やってみます｡
The longer one goes out first.
長い方が 先に消えました｡
And the shorter one...
短い方は…｡
eventually goes out too.
今 やっと消えました｡
Why do you think the longer one went out first?
何で 長い方が 先に消えたのでしょうか？
It has to do with carbon dioxide.
ﾎﾟｲﾝﾄは 二酸化炭素です｡
Carbon dioxide is heavier than normal air (Oxygen). →
二酸化炭素は 普通 酸素より重いのですが →
really...
実は あた…｡
From this point on, think for yourself.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
Now everyone is a thinking crow.
これからは みんなが 考えるｶﾗｽ｡